Friends of True Health Tuesday,
I am so happy to be with you again. This
is Maria Jose Hmel and uh I am very
happy. This is true health Tuesday
as always. Every other Tuesday we uh
live stream and um here we are again as
promised. So I hope you are connecting
true health t with true health Tuesday
and uh I promised you that I would talk
about fasting today the healing power of
fasting.
So invite your friends if you're
interested in this. If you know anybody
who's interested in fasting
uh share this um share this link with
your friends. Uh fasting is something
that's become so popular lately.
So you probably heard about intermittent
fasting. We're going to talk about that.
Uh but there's several kinds of
intermittent fasting. So a lot of people
have questions about that. So we'll talk
about that. So share this link with your
friends. There might be a lot of people
who are interested in that. So put in
the chat where you're connected from. By
the way, you guys pray for me because
I'm flying solo today. I have never done
this on my own.
So, please pray for me. I am my own
producer today. So, please elevate a
prayer for me. We are going to pray, of
course. So, I'm trying to make a mental
note of everything I have to do today.
So, play for me. Pray pray. We are going
to pray. But I just wanted to uh first
of all start off by saying that I'm
flying solo. So if I make mistakes,
please forgive me. Also, uh share this
stream or share the link and share with
your friends uh what this is about. It's
about healing uh the healing power of
fasting.
Put in the chat where you are connected
from. I'm going to try to, you know, put
the also try to remind me if you can.
I'm going to try to put it on the
screen. You know, I am very new at this,
you guys. So, I'm going to try I'm going
to try to do this the right way.
So we're going to talk about fasting. So
let's start with prayer so we can go
ahead and get started with today's uh
topic. So let's start with a prayer.
Dear heavenly father, thank you so much
for the opportunity that you always give
us to connect through technology. Uh no
matter where we are in the world, thank
you so much for True Health Tuesdays and
for Living Mana online church. and we
ask you to be with us today with today's
uh presentation and live stream and uh
bless everything who's everyone who is
connected in Jesus name we pray. Amen.
Oh, we already have someone here from
Tennessee. Thank you Sharon for
connecting with us. So everyone uh put a
one in the chat if you are interested in
this topic. If it's something that uh
you are excited about uh learning uh
because Sharon says she's looking
forward forward to hearing about
intermittent fasting. By the way, this
is some something that uh I um you know,
so let me tell you something real quick.
I'm going to give you a little anecdote.
I have been in the church for I don't
know how many years you guys have. I'm
going to give my age. I'm going to give
up my age a little bit. I've been in uh
in the church for like over 40 years.
And I was one of those people who would
I don't know if anyone relates uh with
me uh on this, but uh I was one of those
people who would say you've probably
read those uh quotes. I actually will
show the quotes in a minute that it's
better to eat two meals rather than
three. And we've those of us who've been
in the church for a long time have read
those quotes many many times. And I have
read those quotes too. And I would say,
"Yeah, but you know, oh, I go to the
gym. I'm too active. I'm this and that
and the other." When COVID came,
um, I was reading a book called The
Circadian Code and by a neurologist.
And I do not recommend what he says
about diet. He is a neurologist after
all. He that is not his strength. So
maybe skip the part about nutrition.
Okay. But what he says about the science
of the circadian rhythm
uh and fasting is it convinced me. So I
was convinced by the science. I am
ashamed to say I was convinced by the
science of the circadian rhythm in
regards to fasting and intermittent
fasting. And it blew me away. It blew my
mind and I started doing it right around
the time of the pandemic when the
pandemic started. And I have to say
around that time I had a torn meniscus
that I was thinking about getting a
surgery for, but I I didn't get a
surgery because my account I had my
husband and I have an HSA account, which
is one of those accounts that you start
saving money for to pay your your
deductibles and your co-ayments and all
that. And it was empty because my
husband had had an accident. And so it
was kind of empty. So I was, you know,
it it's my torn meniscus was bad, but
not as bad. I could still walk.
And I decided to wait for the surgery
until, you know, the account, you know,
filled up a little. And so I hadn't
gotten the surgery yet. When COVID
started, of course, we couldn't do the
surgery. And and I started doing
intermittent fasting. After about a year
of doing intermittent fasting,
I was like, "Oh, what happened with my
torn meniscus? I forgot all about it."
I don't know. I can't prove it
scientifically because my insurance will
not pay for another MRI to see if my
torn meniscus is still torn. So, I can't
tell you what happened with my meniscus,
but it's gone.
That's all I could say. It does not
hurt. It does not bother me. It is gone.
That's all I could say. That's my
personal testimony on what intermittent
fasting did for me in less than a year.
My torment. By the way, the uh
orthopedic surgeon who is an Adventist
told me I asked when I went to when I
went to talk to him, can you do anything
for the torn meniscus? And he said, no,
you cannot do anything for the torn
meniscus. You know, I was hoping that as
an Adventist he would say, "Oh, yeah,
you can eat this, that, whatever." And
he's like, "No, no, no, no, no, no, no.
Torn meniscus will never heal
because it's like a hangail.
This is cartilage. It will never, you
know, stick back, you know, it will
never heal. There's no blood flow to it.
It will never heal." Thank you, Linda,
for joining us from Youngsttown, Ohio.
Put it in the chat if you're uh where
you're where you're joining us from.
So, welcome Linda. Um, so anyway, this
orthopedic surgeon uh anist said it will
never heal. There's no blood flow to it
because it's cartilage.
After a year of doing intermittent
fasting,
it never hurt again and to this day.
Personal testimony. I don't know how I
cannot tell you scientifically how it
happened because like I said
they will never pay for another MRI. So
I don't know what's I don't know what's
in there. I don't know if it's back
healed. I can't tell you. That's all I
can say. It's that my tormeniscus does
not hurt anymore. Praise the Lord.
Dylan, South Carolina, thank you Ashley
for joining us from Dylan, South
Carolina. All right. So again, as
always, you're welcome, Linda. As
always, I always say that I the
information that I will give you today
is not meant to be medical advice. All
right? So everything I say is for
educational purposes only. I am not your
doctor. I'm not even a medical doctor
even though I have a a doctorate degree.
But that doesn't mean that what will you
what you will hear today is meant to be
medical advice. everything. Oh,
somebody's uh joining us from girly,
Alabama. Maxi Shelton, welcome
Trinidad and Tobago.
Welcome M uh Daniel
Sharpie.
Blessings to you. All right. So, the
other thing that I always emphasize is
the importance of
I hope you remember this. Many of you
might not know if you're joining us for
the first time, but I go by this rule
and I hope you join us as well. I mean,
I don't know how many of you uh who are
connected today go by this rule as well.
I recommend it, but you know, it's up to
you. Uh but I use this as the the rule
of my life. I will put it I will blow it
up for you to the law and the testimony.
If they speak not according to this word
is because there's no light in them.
Okay. So I try to use this as my rule
not just for spiritual me uh you know
purposes but also for health purposes.
So everything that I will present today
I try to make it so that it's in harmony
with the Bible and spirit of prophecy.
That's what the this verse for me that's
how I interpret this verse. I don't know
how you interpret Isaiah 8:20 but for me
that's how I have been taught throughout
my years and many many many years in the
church also I think that what we present
should have scientific
um good scientific basis. So I think you
know I always show you this uh graphic
right here which is the the hierarchy of
scientific evidence and I consider just
people's opinions to be very low in that
hierarchy whereas a good quality
evidence should be you know scientific
review or systematic review and meta
analysis and good scientific research to
be good quality and people have asked me
in the past oh why do you use so so much
science when we have the Bible
But sometimes we talk to people who are
not Christians. And in fact, Ellen White
has told us that science is power. The
knowledge of science is indeed power.
And she has told us that it is
especially important in preparation for
the work that is to precede the closing
scenes of Earth's history, which is
right now. Have you noticed what's going
on today? today in the news just look at
the news and it seems that you know it's
like reading the great controversy you
guys I don't know if you agree but uh I
think it's I agree with this other uh
statement that a practical knowledge of
science of human life is necessary in
order to glorify God in our bodies. All
right, but I also want to show you
another one. Okay, so this one's new and
it's relevant for today. Let me blow it
up for you a little bit. Um, okay. Here
we go. Ah, that's the one I was talking
about before. In most cases,
two meal two meals a day. Watch. Two
meals a day are what? Preferable to
three.
Supper when taken at an early hour
interferes with the digestion of the
previous meal. taken later. When taken
later, it is not itself digested before
bedtime. Thus, the stomach itself or
thus the stomach sorry fails to of
securing proper rest. The sleep is
disturbed. The brain and nerves are
wearied. The appetite for breakfast is
impaired. The whole system is
unrefreshed.
Oh my goodness. It's almost as if I'm
reading some kind of uh scientific
research paper because it's exactly what
they have found and it is unready for
the day's duties. That was written in
1903.
Wow. Next. Most people enjoy better
health while eating two meals a day than
three. Others
under their existing circumstances
may require something to eat at supper
time, but this meal should be very
light. Oo. Okay. Interesting. Very, very
light. Okay. Good. Good to know. Let no
one think himself a criterion for all.
Okay. Ooh. Important to read that last
sentence
that everyone must do exactly as he
does. Let us not be judges of anyone.
That is very important. Okay? Because
just because we follow, you know, the
two meal, the intermittent fasting
doesn't mean we should judge anyone for
not doing it. So that's very important.
I think it's important to to remember
that just because we follow a whole food
plant-based diet, we follow the Genesis
129 diet, doesn't doesn't make a judges
of anyone else.
All right? anyone anyway. Okay, let's
move on because I think this topic is so
relevant nowadays
even in the news. Have you seen
articles? Have Have you seen it? You
know, even maybe influencers on social
media talking about why is intermittent
fasting so popular? Not just
intermittent fasting. I would say all
fasting is popular nowadays.
And in fact, of course, fasting has been
known to us in the church, has been
known to the world forever. It's an
ancient practice as you probably know.
In fact, it was practiced by ancient
doctors. So it was used therapeutically
by Greek physicians. So apparently this
person you see on the screen right now
is Hypocrates, a Greek physician from
the fifth century before Christ who
recommended abstinence from food or
drink
to patients who presented certain
symptoms of illness.
Some physicians way back then, you guys
recognized
fasting is an instinct.
Wow.
And certain patients with certain
disease states naturally experience loss
of appetite. Have you noticed that
yourself when you're sick? Have you
noticed that? Naturally, sometimes we
lose appetite. Why? because maybe our
body is telling us something.
Makes sense. Some doctors believe that
giving food during these states was
unnecessary and possibly even harmful
as fasting was thought to be an
important natural part of the recovery
process.
I agree. Do you agree?
Because I have heard people tell me the
exact opposite.
And sometimes we believe the exact
opposite of that. It's frozen. Oh no.
Hello. Hello. Do you see me in now? It
could be my uh internet.
It could be my internet.
I hope. Do you see me again? If you see
me again, please put a one in the chat.
Please put a one in the chat if you see
me again because it could be my
internet. So if you see me, please put a
chat
is please put a chat
or I'm sorry, please put a one in the
chat if you see me. Uno.
Do you see me? Oh no,
I don't see any ones.
Okay. Yes. Ah, I see a one. Yay. Thank
you. Thank you, Jesus. Thank you, God.
Yes. All right. So, what I was saying,
yes, I see more ones. Thank you, God.
Yay. Praise the Lord. We're back. Thank
you, Jesus. Thank you. Thank you for all
the ones, you guys. Thank you. Thank
you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
Okay. I have heard, tell me if you have
heard this before, because I think
there's a lot of people who think this
way. Okay.
When somebody is somebody's sick, you
have to feed them. They need nutrition
to recover. They need more food. More
food. Feed them. Feed them. Feed them.
Feed them. Feed them. Feed them.
I have a friend from church who told me
that the other day,
which is the exact opposite of what, you
know, people like Socrates
thought.
And I think rightly so. Maybe not every
disease, but with some diseases, people
naturally lose their appetite. Maybe for
a good reason.
[Music]
Maybe for a good reason. Okay. Anyway,
uh today
fasting
has shown to have pretty incredible
benefits for the body. Now, let me let
me let me tell you a story. Okay, I'm
going to tell you a story.
of a a young man and you'll see that
this picture is quite old. So this man
this young man back in the 1970s
was an athlete. He competed in the
Olympics or was at least a hopeful
Olympic
figure skater. Okay. So, he was training
to be in the Olympics, but he suffered a
serious leg injury
and was forced to walk on crutches he
could not even bear the weight on his
leg without excruciating
pain. His heel was so swollen and tender
that the mere weight of the sheets
caused intense discomfort
because he placed on the top two in the
country for the event that he was
preparing for for the US Olympic.
The Olympic committee encouraged him to
seek treatment with the top orthopedic
surgeons in the country. After months
though, months, months of needlesticks,
probing, medical tests with the
prominent doctor in the field,
prominent, he was still unable to walk
after a year of pain. So, he was quite
discouraged. His doctors offered no
solution for the swelling and acute
sensitivity
on his injured foot.
Then one day without warning while he
was in the hospital a nurse walked into
the room and told him to take some
medicine because his doctor
um proposed a surgical
plan.
uh he he was going to uh perform some
surgery the next morning
which was some kind of experimental
surgery
and he was outraged because the doctor
had not discussed this with him. He was
he refused to take the drug and he
demanded
to talk to the doctor
uh and he demanded that the doctor
discussed the proposed surgery.
Later the in the day the doctor came
into the room. He actually burst into
the room and was kind of upset. You know
sometimes doctors could be a little bit
arrogant especially surgeons I guess. uh
and he informed the athlete that this
was an experimental surgery
uh that required to promote healing or
that was required to promote healing on
his foot. And he explained that he would
expose the tissues
and he would use the scalpel to
traumatize the area. Okay?
and he would cook he would make like a
checkboard pattern on the tissues in an
attempt to stimulate the area to heal.
This was experimental.
And when he heard this, if this young
man said like, "No way you're doing that
on me. No way.
Like you're I'm not going to be your
guinea pig pig basically." And the
doctor got angry and told him that if he
did not undergo the surgery,
he would never walk again.
Never.
But the young man refused the surgery
anyway
and left the hospital.
He was a young athlete. He was aware.
He remembered that a few years earlier
his father
had arthritis
and that he had restored his health
because of fasting.
So he recalled the articles and the
books that the dad had read on fasting.
This was in the 70s. Okay. Okay. So he
realized that the technique maybe could
be good for him. Maybe maybe maybe it
was his best chance.
So what did he do? He went to a place
called
the Dr. Shelton's Health School. All
right. So this was a place way back in
the 70s where people went to get healed.
Kind of like a sanitarium. kind of like
those ad places back in uh the early
1900s
sort of like that. Okay. Oh, we have
someone Andrea from B uh New Brunswick,
Canada. You've you've uh joined us
before. Welcome back, Andrea.
And uh I read that people tend to lose
appetite and muscles because your body
is batt battling. Okay, I'm gonna put it
up here. Oh, I did it. I I've never been
able to do this before, so this is my
first time.
um is battling the illness using your
immune system and the protein in your
body to recover.
That's a very interesting uh theory.
Very good. Very good. It might be it
might be true. All right. Okay. Thank
you for that comment. Okay. So, back to
the story of this young man. He
determined that fasting uh like I said
was his best chance. So, he travel
traveled to Dr. Shelton's uh school of
health in San Antonio, Texas and fasted.
You would want to know how long. I do
not recommend doing this, okay? This is
could only and should only be done under
medical supervision. There are places
where you can do this kind of long-term
fasting, but should only be done under
medical supervision. Did you hear me?
Only under medical supervision. He did
it for 46 days.
Whoa, that's even longer than Moses.
All right. 46 days.
At the end of the fast, he was able to
walk again.
In just over a year, Heath placed third
at the World Professional Figure Skating
Championship.
Praise the Lord. I don't know. He's not
a Christian, but still, praise the Lord.
Uh, at Dr. Shelton School of Heal of
Health. The young man saw asthmatics
cured.
They uh they no longer needed
medication. People with asthma.
He saw ulcerative colitis patients with
intestinal bleeding who recovered
without medication or surgery.
He saw people with chest pain who had
been told they needed bypass surgery
and they were riding bikes and jogging
for the first time in years.
This young man saw for himself how the
body could heal itself if the causes of
disease were eliminated.
Wow. He was so impressed with what he
witnessed and experienced
that he sought out other practitioners
who had used fasting and natural diets
to cure their patients. And what he
learned from them excited him so much
that he decided to attend medical school
and become a doctor.
in medical school. However,
do you think he saw the same things?
What do you think?
Do you think he saw patients being cured
of asthma without medications, p people
with ulcerative colitis, with internal
bleeding recovered without surgery, or
people with chest pain told that needed
a bypass surgery jogging and riding
their bikes?
No, that's exactly the opposite of what
he saw. In medical school, patients were
treated with conventional modern
methods.
Given large amounts of medication to
control their symptoms, they rar rarely
recovered. Unfortunately, as you know,
as a medical student though, the young
man saw patients that suffer and die
unnecessarily while under the care of
modern science.
Uh but he remained convinced that people
could get better if they knew how to use
fasting and the proper diet to restore
their health. Do you want to know who
this doctor is?
Do you want to know?
Or maybe you already know.
Do you know who this doctor is?
I'll tell you because he's actually well
known. He's written a bunch of books and
I recommend reading his books.
He's only written one book on fasting.
All the rest of them are on diet and the
diet he recommends.
I don't know if he knows is the Genesis
129 diet. He might because he's heard
about Adventist. He might have written
about Adventist in his books. I don't
remember. I read his book so long ago.
He might have mentioned Adventist in his
books because Adventists are talked
about within the circles of uh lifestyle
medicine. He's well known in this field
of lifestyle medicine. Anyway, this
book, this uh doctor's name is Joel
Ferman
and uh I definitely uh recommend reading
his books. He's written extensively on
how you can get better. Oh, no, it's not
Dr. Kellogg. Uh he Dr. Kellogg passed
away a long time ago and Dr. Ferman is
still around. In fact, he uh goes to all
these conferences. Uh you can probably
see him if you go to one of the
conferences on lifestyle medicine and
you can buy his books.
He does see patients actually in uh New
Jersey, but it pro it probably is hard
to get an appointment with him. Uh but
he he's sees patients. He has an active
practice. Interesting, right? Okay. So,
that's Joel Ferman for you guys. So,
look him up. Uh Ashley says, "I have
been doing intermittent fasting since
May." Let's show. All right. There it
is. Oh, since May and have lost 45
pounds and gotten off your autoimmune
meds like Prednazone.
Oh my goodness. All these other medic
other medications like blood pressure
med. Oh wow. What a testimony, Ashley.
Praise the Lord. Prennazone especially
is one of those medications that has so
many side effects. If you can get off
that medication, especially, I mean, of
course, all the other medic gird
medications for GER, they're not really
meant to be long-term medications. And
people really, if they can get off of
them, too. Oh, what a blessing. What a
blessing. Oh, praise the Lord.
Congratulations. What a blessing. So,
see what it can do.
45 pounds.
Wow. Great. Awesome. So,
what happens? How does this happen? I'm
going to try to show you real fast the
physiology behind
fasting. So, we understand what's going
on a little bit. It's not like you, you
know, have to know this, but I think it
helps to understand a little bit what's
going on behind the scenes, so to speak,
inside of the body physiologically.
But, let me blow it up so you can see it
better. During fasting the body is not
directing the energy that take the
digestive system takes a a lot of
energy. Okay, the digestion takes a lot
of energy. So when the digestion is not
happening with that when the digestive
system is resting so to speak all of
that d activity that energy is going to
the healing process.
When we eat late the activity of
digestion can deplete the body's energy
and prevent the healing process that
should be happening at night. During the
night especially is when the
healing, the reparation of tissues, the
cleansing especially of the brain, the
flushing of toxins of the brain that
happens at night. The glimpmphatic
system, look it up later, is happening
at night in the system in the brain
flushing the toxins out of the brain.
That happens in the night when you're
sleeping. So, if you're not sleeping,
that's a problem number one, obviously.
But if your body has food in the
digestive system, if you ate late or not
early enough,
a lot of that energy is going into your
stomach
in the top part of your in intestines,
which is doing the digestion.
that part of the D, you know, like the
um the right outside the stomach
and uh the the first part of the um the
the the tube. Let's let's let's say the
um not the colon, but the the the small
intestine,
the dadinum, that's where the most of
the digestion takes place. Okay? So that
Cshape that you see right there, right
outside the stomach, that's most of the
digestion is taking place. That takes
energy, you guys. So if that's happening
at night, that energy goes to the energy
of the healing, the reparation of
tissues, the cleansing, all of the
rejuvenation that needs to takes place
that needs to take place. It's going
towards that. So how is all the
reparation going to take place?
Would fasting help parasites in the gut?
Maybe, but you might need to take an
antiarasite. There's some herbs that can
help with that. Uh, by the way, and some
seeds that can help with that as well.
I'm at work, but jumped for for a
second. Thank you, Takara. Thank you for
joining us. Thank you. We always like
having you. All right. So,
uh, let me show you
what a healthy and an unhealthy cell
look like comparing the two because an
unhealthy cell, as you can see here,
uh, there's some waste products that are
not being eliminated. So fasting helps
to eliminate the like the cellular
waste. But if you're not fasting, that
energy is not being put into that
elimination.
This is all energy that's going into
digestion. Instead,
the digestion is a very energyintense
process. So here I was talking about the
glimpmphatic
system. It's called glimpmphatic because
it's a mix of the lymphatic system, but
since it's in the brain, it just, you
know, it's it has a slightly different
name. Uh it's in the brain, the
glimpmphatic system. It's the system
that basically flushes out the waste.
You can see it in on the right hand side
there. The neurons, the lymph vessels
and the waste that's now this waste.
It's not like there's something wrong
with you. Okay? It's waste that's
naturally being produced
just by normal activity of the brain.
The brain is very intense organ.
Obviously, everything that's happening
in your brain is normal. It's very
intense. So there's a lot of metab
metabolic activity that needs to happen
that naturally produces waste that needs
to be flushed out every single night.
So that's important to happen. But all
of that energy is going to be again
diverted out if we're eating late.
Especially if we're eating late, we
should not be doing that. We should
avoid doing that. Okay. So fasting
provides the body with the ideal
environment,
for healing,
for detoxifying.
That's that's a real detox. Okay? Real
detox happens at night when you're
sleeping if you provide the right
environment.
That's why intermittent fasting is
really the best fasting because it's the
one, the only really the only kind of
fasting that it's in harmony,
perfect harmony with your circadian
rhythm.
Not that all other kinds of fasting
aren't good. All fasting is good.
Actually, every single kind of fasting
has benefit because the minute you stop
eating, you give your body a break and
your your body is going to go into some
kind of healing process immediately.
So, all fasting by nature is going to
help in some way. But the only kind of
fasting that is in perfect harmony with
the circadian rhythm. Now, what
circadian rhythm you might be asking
yourself, right? I haven't defined that.
All right. I I I threw out the word and
didn't say what it what it is.
Circadian, the word circadian has to do
with day and night, with light and dark.
And as humans, we're not cats. We
weren't created to walk around in the
night or mice. I think also mice are
nocturnal. So, nocturnal animals are the
ones who were created by God to go
outside at night and do whatever they're
doing. We are not.
God created us to wake up in the morning
and go outside and look at the sky and
the sky is blue. That blue light goes
into our eyes and starts stimulating the
brain to wake us up.
That's why when we are at night using
screens bad.
Why?
Because the screen has a blue light. So
when at night you're looking at the
screen, the blue light enters your eye,
stimulates the brain to think it's day.
You got to take out the blue light. You
got to put it in night shift or not use
it at all which is better at night.
Anyway, you see why it's so important to
put the any screen, not just the not
just the phone, your tablet, your TV,
any screen. You got to put it on night
shift and take out the blue light or
else you're telling your brain it's day.
I hope I'm making myself clear.
All right, Malawo Chilmo, good morning.
Good. It's morning for you. I think you
must be in somewhere else. Okay. Your
idea of fasting in short terms like
Christ did put the body on time out.
Yes.
God goes through uh the ordeal with you
all the way for he is within you and
out. You know, let me blow this up. Let
me show everybody what uh he is saying
here.
Uh, the choice not to eat verely grabs
our Lord's attention because all the I
don't know how else to show the rest.
Uh, okay. So, he says,
um,
the choice not to eat barely grabs our
Lord's attention because all the while
he is pleading you to feed him within,
but you won't until he blesses you. Then
he can change your name depending on how
long you asked. That's my idea of
fasting and prayer in a nutshell. A
low-key body tantrumish. That's a very
interesting word. Until you get what you
want by choice. When you finally eat
your and breakfast, God celebrates more
than one than we can fathom. It's a very
nice um idea of fasting. It's basically
I think you what you're saying is
sacrificing your own self and your will
to God. I love that. That's a very nice
concept. Thank you. Thank you for
sharing that. Um, and Ashley says,
"Which is why it's so dangerous to eat
three meals a day plus snacks.
You're not giving your body a break."
You're right. I think. And it keeps
insulin levels high. Ex. Exactly.
Leading to insulin resistance. Thank you
very much. You're so right. Absolutely.
Absolutely. Yes. 100%. All right. So,
intermittent fasting, there's many
kinds, as you might know. You can skip a
meal. That's already intermittent
fasting. Fasting on alternate days. You
probably heard um so some people do the
52. I don't know if you've heard they
fast two days a week, eat whatever they
want, the other five. I'm not sure
that's a great idea. Uh 24-hour fasting.
We've done this at church. I don't know
if you have done this at church. I mean,
I've been in the church for so long. Uh
we've done fasting days, but fasting and
prayers. Sometimes we've done it with
just uh water. Other times we've done it
with juice,
just fruit. I mean, there's all kinds of
fasting, right? And like I said, all of
them provide some kind of benefit.
But uh what we called uh intermittent
fasting that has to do with and the the
early timerestricted eating or
restricted eating which has to do more
with the circadian rhythm and and let's
go back to the circadian rhythm again it
has to do with the day and night rhythm
and as I said humans are created by God
to be awake during the day.
Unfortunately some people work night
shift and that's outside of our control.
I mean, my cousin just graduated from
nursing school, and nurses when they
have to start working, they're going to
work night shift. Now, there are there
is some um some research that has shown
to amilarate because there's going to be
bad uh side effects from working at
night. There's no working around that.
But you can amilarate the effects of
working night shift by not eating during
your work shift. Do not eat during your
work shift. So, you can eat before or
you can eat in the morning when you're
done working, but do not eat during the
night. And there's benefits to that. Uh
so you know it's one way to lessen the
negative effects of working at night and
try to keep the same schedule which is
very hard but if you try to keep the
same schedule constant
and I know how difficult it is because
it's all over the place you know there
sometimes they work four days a week
sometimes they work three days a week
and it's random sometimes it's it's not
the same days as you know every week.
So, it's hard, but if you can try to
keep a steady schedule, it's better.
It's not as bad as if you know you some
days you work, you are asleep during the
night and some days you're not and it's
just all over the place. That's actually
worse. Anyway, but did you know that
every organ in your body has a clock?
Every single organ in your body has an
internal biological clock. It's not just
just in your brain. your pineal gland,
which is the one that releases
melatonin. There's a little gland that
I've actually touched it. You know, I've
had, you know, some people who take
anatomy sometimes and they have
cadaavvers and you actually get to touch
these little things in the brain. It's a
little tiny thing uh inside of the
brain. But it's not the only thing uh
that actually has a clock. There's
another internal clock inside of the
brain that actually is the master clock.
Uh but every single part of your body
has an internal clock. So we were made
to be um directed by this rhythm, the
circadian rhythm. So that's why when we
violate it, we actually pay the price so
to speak. Our uh health suffers when we
do not follow the circadian rhythm. And
so interestingly enough, we were
actually made to eat earlier in the day.
And I will show you that. But if you do
a search, if you go to Google or any
other search engine and you Google
intermittent fasting, this is what you I
mean I just this is what I did, right? I
did a a search and this is the kind of
thing you will find
for intermittent fasting. This is the
popular kind. You fast in the morning,
you skip breakfast.
Yes or no? Have you done any searches to
look for intermittent fasting? What What
do you see the popular kind of fasting
nowadays? You skip breakfast. You start
eating at noon and you eat until 8:00
p.m. Some of them say 9.
Have you seen this
here? I'll show you another one. This is
just I just Googled it. Intermittent
fasting. This comes up. Fasting window
is between 12. Oh, this is really fuzzy.
Sorry about the quality. But basically,
uh, noon and 8:00 p.m.
the 168 method, some of them call it.
Uh, so you're eating until about 8:00
p.m. 9:00 p.m. You um, you skip
breakfast.
Why do you think this might not be best?
Why?
Any ideas?
Well,
I'll
show you something. I'll show you
something. Okay. They have done some
research on this actually. Plenty of
research actually. And they have found
the following things. Okay. I'll show
you something. I'll show you a little
comparison. very uh simple graphic. So
what you see on the top here over here
is basically the typical American
pattern.
Ad liitum is a Greek
expression that means eat whatever at
whatever time. So they basically
represented by a 24-hour clock. Eat at
whatever time 12 hours a day or more.
Actually, Americans eat about 15 hours a
day, honestly. So, eat whatever at
whatever time. And do you see the um
what happens
with that? What are the consequences?
That's the word I'm looking for. What
are the consequences?
Arrow up. Risk for chronic diseases.
That means increase of risk for chronic
diseases. Simple, right?
Now
what we just saw in the previous
graphics
is that you start eating at noon. Let's
say you are delaying your eating window.
So that's called right here the bottom
here. It's called delayed timerestricted
eating. Delay. you delay the eating
window. That's why it's called delay. T
R E. The T re stands for timerestricted
eating.
And do you see what what's in the little
box over here? There's a big question
mark. Why?
Because
the benefits are not so clear.
There is question mark because some
studies show benefits and others do not.
There's mixed results.
Some studies have shown cholesterol goes
up with this.
Some studies have shown people do not
lose weight with this. Some people do,
some people don't. H
question mark.
But do you see what's in the middle?
Do you see that
arrow down risk for chronic disease
decrease
for risk for chronic disease? Do you
want that?
So what are we looking at here then?
What is this early t rear
timerestricted eating? You're not
delaying
the window.
You're eating early.
Early timerestricted eating is the only
modality of intermittent fasting that is
in harmony with the circadian rhythm.
I'll show you. I'm not just talking.
This is evidence-based.
So early timerestricted eating
is when you start eating in the morning.
Eating in the morning. And it has shown
that it improves 24hour
glucose levels and it affects markers of
the circadian rhythm.
Aging.
Do you want to age less fast? Do you
want to age less?
Autophagy.
What is autophagy? You know what
autophagy is? Is when your cells start
eating that waste and
Take it out. Do you want your body to
clean that waste out? Let me blow it up
actually so you can read.
What are we seeing here? That blue says
TRF
timerestricted feeding. Sometimes they
call it feeding. Improved weight loss
and cardioabolic end points such as
insulin levels, insulin sensitivity, and
blood pressure.
when participants ate when
late. No, it says early or in the middle
of the day, but worsened
cardioabolic health or had no effects
when participants ate late in the day.
Clear. Could not be more clear.
Huh?
Look at this. Look, please look, look,
look, look, look.
Because I don't know that you can get
more clear than this.
They compared two groups. Basically,
the group on the left ate whatever.
Typical American pattern. Eat at
whatever time. The group on the right
did what kind? Early timerestricted
feeding. They ate. In fact, they give us
the time right there on the little
plate. They started eating at 8. They
ended at 2. That's pretty small window
actually. It's less than 8 hours. About
6 hours
or is it 8 9 10 11 12 two. Yeah. Okay.
Look at the benefits you guys. On the
left we see the benefits for diabetics
postprandial.
It's a pretty fancy word for after
meals.
So, their insulin after the meals was
less. Why? The answer is the middle.
Because their sensitivity was better. In
other words, because their pancreas was
working better. That's what's beta. That
Greek uh B beta cell. Those are the
cells in your pancreas. They work
better. your pancreas is working better
which is what diabetics want meaning
you had better sensitivity to your
insulin as well so def basically it's
better for diabetics
great awesome okay on the right we see
blood pressure went down which is what
Ashley told us right no somebody else
told us I forgot who told us somebody
told us that they lost 45 pounds I
forgot I have to go back oh yeah Ashley.
Yes, Ashley told us
happens right here too. Oxidative stress
went down.
Appetite. Oh,
please pay attention. Appetite went down
when though. Please pay attention.
The appetite went down when
in the evening.
How is that possible that the appetite
went down in the evening? We've talked
about this before at all.
They're not eating in the evening and
the appetite went down in the evening.
Crazy.
Now, their triglycerides went up. And
you might be thinking, "Oh, that's
terrible. That's a bad thing." I'll tell
you why that happened.
It's because they are in fat oxidation.
These people are burning fat and they do
explain us this in the in the
discussion. If you read the study, they
do give an explanation. They're in fat
oxidation, meaning they're burning fat.
So they come here or they come, you
know, to the research place after 18
hours of fasting. And so they're
actually in in the fat oxidation mode.
They're burning fat. So the fat shows up
in the blood. So that's the discussion.
That's what they said. But I want to
show you something super interesting
here because regarding the appetite
aspect of it. Do you see? I think I
showed you did I show you this last
week, but some people might not have uh
connected last uh time. So I want to
show you these because this has to do
with the appetite aspect of it. in the
far top left,
desire to eat. In fact, the whole row up
on top has to do with appetite. Okay,
desire to eat in the top left. In the
middle, it says capacity to eat and in
the right it says hunger.
And I want you to notice that the dark
bar are the people who fasted whereas
the the white bar are the people who ate
at whatever time and meaning they were
eating dinner. And yet in the evening,
comparing the evening,
their desire to eat of the people who
fasted, the capacity to eat, and the
hunger of look at the black bar
comparing the white bar. The black bar
is shorter, meaning they had less desire
to eat, less capacity to eat, less
hunger than people who were fasting.
And they had less of those things in the
evening. Look at it. Are you looking?
And look at the bottom row now.
Because this is crazy if you think about
it. How can this happen?
How can this happen? Because now we're
looking at fullness.
Fullness.
And stomach fullness in particular.
Okay. What?
They were not eating. Okay. How how do
you explain this?
Because look at the evening
and both the evening
and now look at the dark bar
compared to the white bar in the evening
for fullness and for stomach fullness.
How is it that they're more full if
they're not eating in the evening? They
stopped eating at 2.
What? They were eating air.
Did the air make them feel full?
Explain that.
I'll explain it. Don't worry.
I'll explain it coming up here. I'll
tell you how that happened.
Here's the title of the study you want
to look at. Early timerestricted feeding
reduces appetite.
Do you see
reduces appetite? Look at the yellow
down here at the bottom. Early tiger
restricted feeding also may increase fat
loss by increasing fat oxidation is what
I was just telling you.
Burning fat.
Okay, the next slides just talk about
the insulin aspect of it. So this is
very good for diabetics. there's less
insulin and more beta cell
responsiveness. So, this is great. But I
want to show you something super
interesting for the appetite aspect of
it. Okay, the four things we're looking
at, they're all appetite hormones.
Appetite hormones.
In fact, the one you see at the bottom
right, you might recognize the name.
Do you recognize the name GLP1?
Do you know that name? The other two on
the left, you I don't know. I've been
talking about those for a long time
because one of them stimulates appetite,
the other one reduces appetite.
Now, the fact that ghrein goes down
doesn't help. But the fact that the
other three, you know, the the whole
action of all four of them here, the
whole action of all four of them
combined makes appetite go down. And the
fact that GLP1 goes up in the afternoon
is what I want to want what I want to
really uh point out because GLP1 you
guys GLP1
semiglutide
otherwise known as oampic
is this.
Did you know?
Did you know that intermittent fasting
elevates the levels of GLB1? Well, there
it is. There it is. Now, you know.
Okay. So, here we have some uh things I
haven't showed. Uh
okay. So, wow. Ad libbitum is why we
have Okay, let me show it.
uh ad libitum is why we have fast food
restaurants open until 3
3:00 a.m. causing heart disease to be
rampant in the United States.
Wow, very good comment. Very good
comment. I'm learning about my errors in
intermittent fasting. So thankful. You
are welcome. Very, very welcome. All
right, let me show you some more stuff,
you guys. Uh some more interesting
information. I know this is very
sciency, so you got to forgive me for
some of this stuff, but I just want to
show you. Okay, this is from Adventist
study uh two, health study 2, because it
will bust some myths, I think. Uh this
is talking about subjects who ate one or
two meals a day. I don't recommend
eating one meal a day. Two meals is
great. Okay, look at the results. Okay,
look at the where it says results. It
says subjects who ate one or two meals a
day had a reduction of BMI. What does
that mean? BMI weight
compared to those who ate three meals.
Um, okay. So then it says jump where it
says breakfast. Okay. Breakfast eater
right in the middle of the paragraph.
Breakfast eaters experienced a decrease
of BMI. In other words, they lost more
weight compared to breakfast skippers.
Relative
to subjects who ate their largest meal
at dinner,
those who consumed breakfast as their
largest meal experience a significant
decrease in BMI.
Ah, conclusions.
Our results suggest that in relatively
healthy adults, eating less frequently,
no snacking,
consuming breakfast, and eating the
largest meal in the morning may be
effective methods for preventing
longterm weight gain.
Eating breakfast and lunch. What meals
again? breakfast and lunch five to six
hours apart and making the overnight
fast last 18 to 19 hours. That sounds
like a lot, but you're going to feel
less hunger. Remember,
maybe useful practice strategy.
You might be thinking, "No way I can do
that. Oh, that sounds like way too long.
18 19." You're going to elevate GLP1 and
you're not going to be paying $1,000 a
month for Ompic or Wikov.
I'm just saying you don't have to do it,
okay? Nobody's going to force you. This
is all
optional.
Optional, optional.
Okay, let's see what Ashley says. I
wanted to share I came on I came on for
one of your first shows. You shared the
book of Goodbye Loop. Yes, I did share
that and I read it and then committed to
vegan whole food eating and have been
using fasting from 400 p.m. to to 10:30
a.m. Wow. Well, good for you. Praise
God. Thank you for sharing that. Thank
you so much. All right. I want to show
you guys that when they did the study,
remember I told you about the uh people
who started eating at noon? They did do
the study and what did they find? Let me
show you. Uh if you go down to so this
is an 168 also just like the people who
did the other study. This is a 12week
study. If you read that right there
where it says design setting and
participants
where it says intervention
they do say they started at 12 they uh
ended at 8:00m. Okay. And down at the
bottom, conclusions and relevance. It
says timerestricted eating in the
absence of other interventions is not
more effective in weight loss than
eating throughout the day.
What? I thought it was effective.
So, how come they're saying it's not
effective?
You have to look at the you you have to
look at the whole thing. Do look at what
time they ate. So see see if you just if
you just listen to the headlines
you might say oh you know in the news
they said that you know uh intermittent
fasting doesn't work.
Yeah. But what did they do? What did
they actually do? They ate from 12 to 8.
If you go back to the Adventist health
study it did work. They did lose weight.
What time did they eat? breakfast and
lunch.
You see,
that's why it's good to read the
science.
But if you don't want to read it, it's
okay. You have people like me. I'll read
it for you and then I'll tell you what
it says. That's fine. No problem. I
don't mind doing it. All right. I'll
tell you something else. Circadian
clocks and insulin resistance.
H. What about it? Well, it just so
happens that glucose tolerance
is higher
in the morning
than in the evening.
I'll repeat it. Glucose
tolerance,
what does that mean?
Is highest in the morning?
Meaning when you eat in the morning,
that food is going to be metabolized
better, especially your carbohydrates
than in the evening.
So if you're going to have a big potato
in the evening,
your blood glucose in the morning
fasting is going to be way higher.
So people come to me to my program.
I tested their their fasting blood
glucose last Sunday. Had some diabetics
with 200 something fasting blood
glucose.
I'm like, "What did you eat last night?"
"Oh, you know, I was at a birthday party
and the
what do you expect?"
You know, I'm sorry. I just can't, you
know. So, you know, what should I do?
Try to eat early. If you're going to
have dinner, make it very light. If
you're diabetic, eat a salad. Don't put
any carbs.
Seriously, I'm not saying that you need
to go on a restricted carb diet, but
right now you are not controlling
anything right now. So, you are your
insulin resistance off the charts. So,
go on a whole food plant-based diet, but
while your um your insulin resistance is
bad,
just don't eat carbs at night because
your your fasting blood glucose is
really bad. So, eat a salad. Eat a salad
or eat soup with vegetables or don't eat
anything even better.
What do you think?
But Oh, no. No, no, no, no, no, no. I
used to work at a clinic and even when I
would tell that to diabetics,
no, no, no, no. You can't tell that to
diabetics.
Diabetics need to eat six times a day,
every two hours,
or else
Oh, it's practically like they're going
to die. But oh my god, no. Really? Is it
that bad if they eat only twice a day?
Are their blood sugars going to go all
over the place? They're going to be out
of control. Really? Is it?
What does the evidence say? Oh, they
never wanted to compare evidence. But
let me show you the evidence. Okay, you
want to see the evidence? Let's see it.
Let's look at it together.
Eating two meals. How many? Wait, what?
What? No. Wait, what? Two meals a day?
Which meals? Breakfast and lunch
is more effective than six smaller meals
in a reduced energy regimen. In other
words, they put them in a low calorie
diet for patients with what?
Type 2 diabetes.
No way.
More effective than six meals a day. If
you want, take a picture of this or come
back later. You can look it up. You can
actually read the study and see for
yourself.
Diabetics do better on two meals a day.
I didn't say it.
They said it. Here is their conclusion.
You can look it yourself. Let's read it
together.
Eating only breakfast and lunch in a
reduced and uh lunch reduced body
weight. In other words, they lost uh
they lost uh weight. Wait, hold on. They
lost weight
and uh HFC,
which means um
hold on one second. And what are they
talking about? Uh, hi. Hold on. One
second. I'm sorry. I didn't prepare for
this because I forgot what HFC um, well,
let's just skip it for right now. But,
uh, fasting plasma glucose, C peptide,
and glucagon increased
um,
insulin sensitivity. That O GIS is an
measured uh, measurement of insulin
sensitivity.
and
more than same caloric restriction split
into six meals. These results suggest
that for type 2 diabetic patients on a
hypoenergetic diet, eating larger
breakfast and lunches may be more
beneficial than six smaller meals a day.
What do you think? What do you think
about that? What do you think? Are you
convinced?
You can tell your diabetic friends now.
Wow. Now look at this one. Look at this
with me. Prolonged fasting overnight.
Prolonged fasting overnight was
associated with 4% lower 2hour glucose
measurement and 3-hour increase in
nighttime fasting duration associated
with 20% reduced odds for elevator A1C
which is another measure for glucose.
Conclusion, longer time, nighttime
duration was significantly associated
with improved glycemic regulation. And
all of that
improved breast cancer risk.
I don't know if you knew, but high blood
glucose puts people at higher levels of
cancer. Those two are connected.
This is from the Obesity Society. Look
at the times that they measured for the
obesity society. Okay, this is for
weight loss. I'm gonna blow it up really
big so that you can see it. And in the
paragraph right there says early
timerestricted feeding can increase fat
burning. Do you like the sound of that?
Fat burning at night and reduce hunger
swings. Hunger swings. We already talk
about talked about how that can happen.
It has to do with the hormones. So it
says reduce hunger swings. Two key
factors in losing weight. So the fat
burning and hunger swings in the nef
which is early time restricted feeding.
People eat their last meal in mid
afternoon
and don't eat again until breakfast the
next morning.
So there you go. I hope you have enough
evidence. I hope that's I hope that's
enough evidence. I hope that uh you have
seen the benefits. Uh but you know what?
It's not just that. There's so I mean we
can be all day. I'm just going to go
through the legs very very fast because
we've been here long enough. So I just I
just want to tell you because I'm just
you can see how excited I am about these
things. But I just wanted to show you
for instance for our immune system. I
started learning about these things with
COVID. COVID is back this year. So, you
might want to know that intermittent
fasting uh it could help you in as your
for your defenses basically uh for your
immune system.
uh it it re it basically improves the
immune response and autophagy and I
already said what that is is when your
body basically cleans up your your cells
eat the waste. So as a healthy practice
calorie restriction in the form of
intermittent fasting in several clinical
settings has been reported to promote
several health benefits including
priming the immune response. So this
dietary restriction also activates
autophagy, a cell surveillance system
that boost up boosts up immunity. It
improves immunity. Isn't that great? I
think it's awesome. So let your friends
know it improves immunity. Also, it
reduces inflammation. So here's another
one that also has to do with immunity
because it's connected to inflammation.
So the highlights are over here. You
could see here at the bottom. So fasting
reduces the number of circulating
monocytes and healthy humans and mice.
Fasting also reduces monocy metabolic
inflammatory activity. So you could see
you know the benefits for both
inflammation reduces inflammation and
boosts immunity antimicrobial immunity.
It even talks about over here. So the
benefits are uh have been confirmed both
for uh immunity and inflammation.
Now look, it can also improves your lip
lipids
and cognitive function by the way. So
this is talking about cognitive function
and older adults. So for people who are
older,
uh yeah, they're going to need an
appropriate diet. They need to be
consuming the right amount of calories
for their for their age. You don't want
them to be losing weight. So make sure
they eat abundant abundant amount of
proteins and carbohydrates and fats. But
that doesn't mean that they're not going
to benefit from doing intermittent
fasting because it improves cognition,
cognitive
function.
And it even says adults with mild
cognitive impairment. It might improve,
you know, their cognitive function. So
why not? I think it's a great idea. All
right. Um lipids, I was saying. Okay.
Improves lipids. So we're talking about
you know uh the um cholesterol and
triglycerides. So that can help to
prevent or manage or even treat
cardiovascular disease. So we have been
talking before about diabetes,
pre-diabetes, high blood pressure and
all these other things. Oh, somebody's
joining us from Papa New Guinea and
South Pacific Ocean. So Johnson uh OBJ
and R welcome and thank you for joining
us. Uh so intermittent fasting for
cardiovascular health. Excellent. All
right. So see how I'm going fast through
these because these are just I'm just
mentioning things. This is for mental
health you guys. So let me take myself
out so you can see it better although
it's hard to read. But the one on the
left talks about the efficacy of fasting
and calorie restriction on mood and
depression.
So it helps with depression. The one on
the right talks about the 8hour
timerestricted eating for people. And
and here's talking also about um mental
health. But if you read the conclusion
down at the bottom, it's talking about
depression and sleep quality. So it's
also talking about the benefit for
mental health. So mental health and
depression in both uh in both of these
studies it found that it could uh have
this positive effect for mental health.
So I think that's great news. All right
look at this. This is I think one of the
most amazing things that I have read
about fasting in the last few years and
is that people who have cancer and are
going through chemotherapy
this is amazing. I think it's
revolutionary honestly
if they do fasting for at least 48 to 72
hours and they can they don't have to do
water fasting only. There's a there's a
protocol called the fasting mimicking
diet. So they're basically eating a low
calorie but it's a very special diet
that's been formulated to mimic the
effects of water fasting. So it's not
just any diet. So it's a very special
diet that has the ex exact same ex exact
same effects as water fasting in the
metabolically speaking. So if they
either do water fasting or the fasting
mimicking diet prior to chemotherapy, so
like the couple days before they receive
the chemotherapy,
what it does is that it sensitizes the
tumor cells to the chemotherapy, meaning
it makes them more more vulnerable to
the chemotherapy and basically they die
more with the chemotherapy while at the
same time protecting normal cells. cells
from the damages
of the chemotherapy treatment. In other
words, it protects good cells while
damaging more the tumor cells which
means that the people who are receiving
the chemotherapy will have less side
effects because the normal cells will be
less affected by the chemotherapy which
is as you know it's very very toxic.
uh so it results in less side effects
for patients
receiving chemotherapy. So this has been
quite revolutionary. Uh so they're you
know they're studying it in UCLA and
they're studying it in Italy because the
main researcher is from Italy. So he's
written books about this and they're
doing and honestly the fasting mimicking
diet is so excellent that they're using
it for other purposes as well not just
for cancer but it was initially studied
for the purposes of cancer. Uh so they
showed you know the benefits. I I'll
just skip the this graphic because it's
a little bit hard to read but I'll go to
the other uh other of these studies that
they have done of the protective effects
for chemotherapy using this fasting uh
for you know the stem cells that are in
these tumors. So it will you know damage
the stem cells from the chem protect the
good stem cells and damage the stem
cells of the tumors and the um
in the tumors and doing while doing
chemotherapy it and it actually helps
with aging. So it's amazing. It's
amazing all these things that I'll just
go really quick because we're out of
time. But I here's another one if you
want to read it. you know, I'll just
I'll just show it to you because it says
fasting potentiates the anti-cancer
activity of some of these enzymes. And
uh it's amazing what the what it here
shows what fasting alone, fasting with
um with chemotherapy and chemotherapy
without fasting. And the best of all
results was the fasting with the
chemotherapy.
And last of all, I want to tell you
that the keto diet, interestingly
enough,
was invented
because
fasting originally was shown to help
patients with epilepsy.
But the thing is children
who have epilepsy
well it's really hard to fast ch you
know to put children on a fasting
protocol because children are growing
and how are you going to put children on
a fasting protocol they need to eat
right I mean that was the thinking so
fasting children you know was hard so
they were studying you know the um the
fasting the effects of fasting and as
you can see here the history of the keto
diet or whatever and back in 1921 I
don't know if you could see it up there
they started using the keto diet KD
instead of fasting it says right there
because they found that the keto diet
had similar effects to fasting. So in
other words, fasting was used first for
treating epilepsy
and then they found that the keto diet
had a similar effect to the keto diet or
to you know basically the the the keto
diet has similar similar effects to
fasting. And that's when the keto diet
was invented.
The keto diet today people use it to
lose weight. It's the best thing in the
world. blah blah blah keto diet. But the
point of it all is that the original
keto diet is fasting.
I hope I made that clear. the original.
That's why back here when I went back
here, okay, intermittent fasting, see
the title, a new and they're putting new
quote unquote new historical strategy
for controlling seizures. It's not new
because it was done way back in the past
before they invented the keto diet. But
the original keto diet is fasting. So
when you hear, "Oh no, but the keto diet
has this and that and the other
benefit,"
always remember
that all those benefits
can be obtained from the original
keto diet which was d which was fasting.
And you do not need to put, by the way,
those children who were put on the uh
keto diet instead of fasting
then had years later terrible
consequences for their cardiovascular
health because they were eating a
highfat diet. That's what the keto diet
is, a highfat diet. So they were eating
this, right? Eggs, meat, bacon,
whatever. And so all of these things
after many years of eating them, they
were had the the side effects of having
terrible cardiovascular health. So that
you have to take into account when
treating children for epilepsy with the
keto diet.
So you can obtain the benefits of the
keto diet without the side effects by
going to the original fasting. So, thank
you for joining us uh today for this uh
presentation. I'm going to leave you
with uh this wonderful wonderful verse.
I'm going to give credit where credit is
due. I obtained this uh beautiful
graphic from Marilyn and Sarah
Ministries. But the verse is from 1
Corinthians 6:19 and 20. How many of you
know this beautiful verse? It says, "Or
do you not know
that your body is what? A temple of the
Holy Spirit within you,
who you have from God. You are not your
own, for you were bought with a price.
So glorify God in your body. Glorify God
in your body. Glorify God in your body.
Your body is a temple.
You know, I just think this is so
important nowadays more than ever
because the first angel message says to
give glory to God. This is part of the
first angel's message. In my humble
opinion, this is part of the first angel
message. How do we glorify God?
By remembering that our body is a temple
of the Holy Spirit. I remember seeing
many many years ago a headline from the
Los Angeles Times, which is, you know, a
big newspaper,
uh, from California, obviously, and it
said, "Why Adventists live longer than
the rest of us."
This is Los Angeles time. Why
Adventists?
No, it said why Lomal Linda residents.
And of course, people know about the
blue zones, right? So said, "Why Lomma
Linda residents
live longer than the rest of us."
This is the headline, you guys. And down
at the bottom, the second line of the
headline said, "Because they treat the
body as a temple."
What a testimony to the world. What a
testimony to the world. I have the
outmost respect
for people in Lomma Linda who today
they're 90 95 100 plus
because they treated their body as a
temple
back in the 1950s and60s
early when all those research studies
the Adventist health study one Adventist
health study 2 and all these other
things and all these other studies that
are on health adventist health studies
were published. They didn't exist.
All they had was to the law and the
testimony. That's all they had, you
guys. They went by faith
and they treated their body as a temple
and they put Lomalinda literally on the
map.
Literally.
Literally. Because when I go to those
big conventions, you know, the
conferences and there's thousands of
people there, I'm talking huge
conferences.
99% of them are non-adventists
and they're talking about health
adventist study, health this and that
and blah blah blah and longevity and the
whole food plant-based diet and you
know, lifestyle medicine.
Health Adventist study. Is there any
Adventist here
in the audience? And there's like four
of us amongst this sea of people, right?
And we are like, yeah, oh, great. You
know, like, congratulations. Basically,
they know us.
But you know what? It's sad. It's sad
because I talk to people
amongst the sea of people who think we
all eat like that.
It's kind of sad. I feel bad telling
them the truth. I feel dishonest if I
don't, right? I have to burst their
bubble. And you know,
we don't all eat like that. We don't all
follow the eight principles of health,
which is almost the same as the American
College of Lifestyle Medicine. It's
almost the same principles
validated by help by by the science of
today. the eight principle or the
principles of the American College of
Lifestyle Medicine, every single one
evidence-based. That's why it's they're
showing them every single one of our
principles.
The eight principles of health, the
eight laws of health, every single one
has been validated
by solid scientific evidence. Solid
functional medicine, integrative
medicine, not so.
Not so the yoga or the meditation all
the others. No. Does not have the solid
uh scientific base. No. No.
But the eight principles of health from
God. Yes. Every single one of them.
Every single one.
Praise the Lord. Praise the Lord.
So I will leave you once again. if you
have any questions. By the way, there's
still a little bit of time, but Amen.
Amen. Thank you. You're welcome for the
information.
Uh, so here's the last few comments. Uh,
thank you for this information. Amen.
Wonderful class. Thank you for your
comments. See how I'm I'm learning to be
my own uh producer. I didn't know how to
do this. Oh, but now I'm learning. Uh,
so website right here. By the way, sorry
you guys if I have not answered any of
the if you've sent me in the last two
weeks. So, I'm going to reveal something
today. If I haven't responded any of
your messages, if you have uh been
sending me any messages, the reason why
is because I'm going to give you some
news. I got accepted into a program in
Lumalinda University. Can you believe
it?
my second doctorate degree.
It's all a miracle. It's all
providential, I have to tell you. Uh you
know, when God is in something because I
had applied to other things and I was
like, "No, no, no." All the doors were
closed. Every single one of those doors
were closed. And by pure coincidence,
I happened to, you know, bump into this
program. Pure, you know, I don't know. I
just have to say it's a little miracle
that happened. And um the admissions
were closed back in February. I wasn't
supposed to
start next week, but God opened the
doors. He knows why he's doing this. So
I'm in
not 2026, you guys. I'm in next week. So
God knows why. Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you for your congratulations.
Thank you. Praise the Lord. He knows why
he's putting me there. So, it's a doctor
of public health, my second doctorate.
So, it's a doctorate of public health uh
in preventive care, which is exact same
thing that I'm doing now. It's all, you
know, lifestyle medicine. So, if I have
not answered anything you have sent me
in the last two weeks, it's because of
that I've been like insane. Uh just
crazy. So, but anyway,
thank you for congrat for your
congratulations. But what I wanted to
say is uh I'll check today. Tonight I
promise if you send me anything to my
website I will check today
healthfor.net.
If you have any questions regarding
today's uh presentation I will make I
always I have been faithfully making the
PDF with the slides and sent it to the
graphics team and they're all available
so far. They have been and feel free to
use them. Feel free to use any of the
slides that I have shared. If you want
to make your own presentations with this
uh material, do it. Share it. Share it.
Make presentations. Have a little uh
Bible study group or whatever. Have a
ministry. Do it. This is the time. This
message is for today. Now. Now. Do you
know how much uh
health insurance rates are going to
start going up? It's scary.
And the spirit of prophecy told us we're
going to have to be our own doctors at
some point. I think that point's coming
because,
you know, it's going to be hard. It's
going to be hard. It's going to get
harder. So, we need to take control of
our own lives. We need to prevent
prevent
prevent more than ever.
The information we have is so valuable.
The world needs it more than ever. It's
time to share it. It's time to live it.
A blind person cannot guide another
blind person. So, we can't share
something we're not living. I mean, we
we need to experience it in our own
lives. So, thank you for all the
congrats. Thank you. Uh thank you for
for being here. Oh, eye opening
information. I'm I'm very glad it's eye
openening for you. Again, feel free to
use it. Um let's see what this one says.
Just about to ask if it's available it
and it will be okay to share.
Absolutely.
Modern medicine is you know
unfortunately sometimes
you know they haven't been taught this
information because just you know how it
is. This the status quo is what they've
been taught in school. They haven't been
gi unfortunately some of it is trickling
in now. You know some of this lifestyle
medicine is trickling in into some
medical schools and you know Lomal Linda
is being pioneer in some of this. The
only masters in public health in whole
food plant-based nutrition is in Lomol
Linda University. I know people who are
not Adventists who want to take it. So,
praise the Lord. We are really,
you know, working hard at uh at, you
know, doing this. So, it's amaz. It's
amazing. So, thank the Lord. You know,
this by the way, this program I'm doing
is 100% online. So, some people are
doing it from all over the world. Is
amazing. So if you want to download the
10day challenge is on my website
health4today.net
try for 10 days if you have not ever
done a whole food plant-based diet. I
want to tell you that in this 10day
plan,
there is one or two pages on how to do
intermittent fasting
to
turbocharge weight loss. If you're
really having a hard time, if you're
really, really, really having a hard
time losing weight, which a lot of
people do,
it's in there. So, not only, you know, a
plan. So, some people might need to do
three meals a day to get started because
sometimes doing everything all at once
might be really, really hard. So, the
original plan is three meals a day, but
if you want to do two meals, I show you
how to do it. Okay? So, there's a two
meal plan or a guide on how to do two
meals as well. And there's, you know,
shopping list, obviously, the recipes,
all of that. So I call it the Daniel
plan because
Daniel chapter one shows you that in 10
days you can see the difference. I see
the difference every time I do a round
of my program. You know I do this for a
living, right? You know I've told you I
do this for a living. In 10 days I see
people's the one biometric that goes
down the fastest
is LDL
cholesterol.
Number one cause of death in the United
States and the whole world actually is
cardiovascular disease. Heart disease is
the number one cause of death. And the
number one risk for heart disease is LDL
cholesterol. Did you know LDL
cholesterol sticks inside of your
arteries and starts to block them? Once
one of those arteries is blocked, you
get a heart attack.
And the one biometric that goes down the
fastest with God's diet is LDL
cholesterol.
It's amazing.
The cure for the number one cause of
death in the world is God's diet.
I don't know. You see how passionate I
am about this? is because it's just
amazing. It's amazing. It's amazing.
It's amazing. Okay. What's the Yaka app?
I've never heard of this Yaka app. Oh,
maybe I have actually. It has helped me
to avoid unhealthy foods, hair products,
medicines. Well, I'm going to have to
look it up. Thank you for sharing,
Christie.
Since my gallbladder was removed one
year ago. I cannot. Yes, of course. So,
so when your gallbladder is removed, you
guys, you have nowhere to store that
um liquid that helps you to uh digest
the fats, right?
Where are you going to store it? Now,
the gallbladder is what stores it.
So, now you cannot eat large amounts of
fat all at once. Do not do it or you're
going to live in the bathroom.
You know what I'm talking about, right?
So, yes, you cannot eat many things you
did in the past. That is correct. Amen.
Says pin pen pen.
You're welcome, says Christie. Thank you
for sharing. So, that's I'm going to put
it up again. So, the app is called Yaka
Yuka. Yuka Yaka Yuka. I'm gonna look it
up. Thank you. That's very very
helpful, very interesting.
Okay, you guys, 1 hour and 39 minutes.
Sorry, I get as you know, so excited
about this stuff. All right, so promised
I will make the PDF for this. Use it,
spread the word. Um, yeah, feel free,
feel free. And once this uh recording is
done, it's going to be on YouTube. Uh
Living Mana Online Church, Power Part of
the Lamb is going to be on Facebook. I'm
going to put in my Facebook as well. And
you can share it. Uh if you are
connecting on on uh YouTube, make sure
to like, what is it that you have to do?
Always like and share, subscribe to the
channel, all those nice things that you
always hear because it helps the channel
to grow and reach more people. See, I
learned to say all those the right
things. Oh, somebody shared something.
Let's see. Walter White for thought was
great. Oh, I'm gonna have to check that
up. All right. Yeah, Walter White.
Awesome. All right, you guys. Let's
finish with prayer. Okay, so let's bow
our heads and let's finish with a word
of prayer.
Thank you Lord for everything you do for
us and thank you for giving us the
health message and giving us the
blessings of fasting so that we can
improve our health, clean our bodies and
thank you for helping us to understand
the importance of treating our bodies as
a temple. We ask for your Holy Spirit
tonight that it may give us wisdom and
understanding and also the motivation to
do the right thing so that we may
glorify you in our bodies. be with
everyone connected tonight and also
everyone who will see this recording in
the future so that you this message will
spread and more people will learn that
you have designed our bodies in such a
way that it can heal itself.
We ask and pray all these things in
Jesus' name. Amen. Thank you again
everyone for connecting. See you in two
weeks. By the way, oh, I can't forget to
tell you that in two weeks I will be I
was impressed to talk about nutrition
and the brain. This is one of my
favorite topics and I usually do two
aspects of nutrition in the brain in one
presentation, but I was impressed that I
need to split it. So, because they're
two both too important. So I'm going to
talk about first about neurodeenerative
diseases such as uh you know dementia
and Alzheimer's disease and all these
things first. So that's in two weeks but
in four weeks I'm going to talk about
mood disorders. So depression and
anxiety for the most part. So that's in
four weeks. So um September 30th
Alzheimer's and prevention of
Alzheimer's for the most part but also a
little bit of Parkinson's disease as
well. So those are neurodeenerative
diseases and September 14th I will talk
about mood disorders and nutrition. So
this is all related to nutrition. Okay.
So nutrition and the brain September
30th and October 14th. Uh those are the
two coming up. So put in your calendar,
share the word. Thank you again. Good
night everyone and God bless you. See
you in two weeks. And uh good night and
thank you for connecting. God bless you.
Good night.
Amen and good night.